The musical experience of a generation becomes a motion picture event
High School Musical 3: Senior Year is a comedy,
romance, drama film directed by Kenny Ortega.
As seniors in high school, Troy and Gabriella struggle with the idea of
being separated from one another as college approaches.
Along with the rest of the Wildcats, they stage a spring musical to
address their experiences, hopes and fears about their future.
Troy Bolton, played by Zac Efron.
Gabriella Montez, played by Vanessa Hudgens.
Sharpay Evans, played by Ashley French.
Ryan Evans, played by Lucas Grabeel.
Chad Danforth, played by Corbin Bleu.
Taylor McKessie, played by Monique Coleman.
High School Musical 3: Senior Year is a 2008 American teen musical film
directed by Kenny Ortega and written by Peter Barsocchini.
The sequel to High School Musical 2 (2007) and the third installment of the High School Musical film series, the film follows Troy Bolton (Zac Efron), Gabriella Montez (Vanessa Hudgens), Sharpay Evans (Ashley Tisdale), her twin
brother Ryan Evans (Lucas Grabeel), Chad Danforth (Corbin Bleu), and Taylor McKessie (Monique Coleman), who are in their final year of high school and face the daunting prospect of being separated as they go off to college.
Joined by the rest of their East High classmates, they stage their last spring
musical, reflecting their experiences, hopes, and fears about the future.
High School Musical 3: Senior Year was developed immediately
following the success of its predecessor.
Production returned to Utah for which Disney received a $2 million tax-break
incentive, the largest the state has ever given to a film.
Principal photography began in May 2008, and Walt Disney Pictures diverted a larger
production and marketing budget to accommodate a theatrical release.
The production returned to previous filming locations East High School and Murray
High School, while additional scenes were filmed in Los Angeles.
An early airing of the film High School Musical 3: Senior Year took place on channel
Jetix Eastern Europe (Russia/CIS, Romania, and Bulgaria) on July 14, 2008.
High School Musical 3: Senior Year premiered in London on October 17, 2008, and was theatrically released
in the United States on October 24, making it the only theatrical release in the franchise.
Upon release, the film proved to be a moderate critical success, with some critics noting it as an improvement over the
previous two installments due to the more emotional tone and themes, while many praised the higher production values.
The film was also a commercial success, as it grossed $90.5 million worldwide in its first three days
of release, setting a new record for the largest opening weekend for a musical film.
Overall, the film grossed $252.9 million worldwide.
The film's soundtrack was also successful, debuting and peaking at
number two on the Billboard 200 in the United States.
A spin-off film, Sharpay's Fabulous Adventure (2011), was
released direct-to-video and on television.
The film explores themes of high school, musical,
sequel, coming of age, high school student.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.